[Music]
hi everyone this is Ravi welcome to Tri
and tasa automation tutorial as you all
know I have already published 35 YouTube
videos covering different topics of tyst
tasa
Automation and in terms of advanced
level con ceps I've covered almost 20
YouTube videos I would recommend you
guys to please go through those videos
before you watch this session this is
our lesson 35 in terms of overall TSA
automation tutorial and it is lesson 20
in terms of advanced level Concepts so
in this lesson I'm going to cover how
can
we connect with your Excel engine which
means how can you perform different
operations related to excel workbooks by
using trient tasa so I'm going to teach
you how can you create our open and
existing Excel sheets and then how can
we modify values within the Excel sheet
right and then how can you save the data
within the Excel sheet and then how can
we close the Excel sheet please do
subscribe to the channel click on Bell
icon you'll receive notifications
whenever I publish more videos thank
you okay what is our agenda so in this
lesson you learn how can we open and
create Excel workbooks by using
triena and also how can you create Excel
worksheet within the Excel workbook
and how can you define the Excel range
within the
worksheet and then how can you
manipulate the Excel range which means
how can you modify or enter the data
within the Excel
sheet and how can you save and close
your Excel workbook after modifying the
data within the Excel sheet so now let's
jump onto the system and see how can we
perform all these operations by using
trien tasa so this is my trient tasa so
let us first create one folder okay the
folder name is
Excel
engine
operations and within this folder I'm
going to create one test case
called
Excel operations okay so now in this
particular test case let us
start creating the Excel operations
related test steps okay what is our
agenda first you need to open or create
Excel workbook okay so for that you need
to right click and then add test
step here I'm going to call an Excel
operation called open Excel workbook so
this is your standard module within the
tbox engine under Excel
okay so I'm going to call this I'm going
to
say what is the workbook name so if you
see here open Excel workbook tbox engine
you need to provide the workbook name so
let me provide the workbook name as demo
and what is the path that you want to
create an Excel workbook I want to take
the documents okay let's take the path
of this okay go to
properties and this is my path copy the
path
and then paste the path here and I need
to append with my demo
dot
xlsx
xlsx okay so and then do you want to
create the Excel workbook new yes
because I don't have the Excel sheet
created in this particular folder so I
want to create it as a new let's select
true so once once you create your Excel
workbook I need to create Excel
worksheet okay for that again let's go
contr t
here you need
to create call create Excel worksheet so
if you see this is your create Excel
worksheet Okay click on
this and here you need to again provide
workbook name what is the workbook name
that we've defined earlier a
demo and then what is the worksheet name
that you want to create I want to create
a worksheet name called
tasa and then what is the worksheet
order that means whatever the worksheet
taskar that you are creating within the
workbook what is the order do you want
to create as a first tab second tab or
third tab right so you can
select I will be selecting it as first
tab so let us now run these two together
and see run these
together and see if it creates your
Excel workbook and the Excel worksheet
so run successful you go to your
documents let's click on date modified I
can see there is no Works Excel sheet is
created why because tasa does not save
Excel workbook unless you save it so for
this there is another operation
called save Excel workbook okay so let
me do one thing so there is another
obervation called close not save close
Excel workbook when you are closing the
Excel workbook there itself you can
provide command or argument whether you
want to save it or not okay let me save
this now so what I'm going to do what is
the workbook name again the same name
what you provided earlier what is the
path that you want to um save this I
want to save the same path where I
created right and then save true or
false you can select save true so now
save this now it let us run all these
three steps together right click and run
now we will see what
happens now it should create your Excel
workbook so let's go to
our
documents and then just simply modify
see now I can see the Excel workbook
demo open this and you have to see the
tab tasa in the order one see this is
your first
TOS okay successfully we created now
what is our next agenda our next agenda
is we opened your Excel workbook our
created workbook and then we created
Excel worksheet and we saved it but now
before you save it I want to define the
Excel range what do you mean by Excel
range I want to define the Excel range
where what I mean so basically I want to
Define excel range like this if I Define
A1 and K 20 that means I want to
manipulate Excel data within this range
A1 K A 1 column a first row column K
20th row right so I want to Define that
kind of excel range so what I'm going to
do I'm going to define the Excel range
as like this
A1 probably like p 50 let's say 50 I
have a table with two columns and 50
rows okay so that's we that's what we
are going to do okay let's go back here
now for defining the Excel range there
is an operation called control
T
Define excel range this is also from
standard modules whatever the Excel
operations all are from standard modules
okay select this one and now let me
Define the Excel name what is the
workbook name same workbook whatever we
created and same worksheet that we
created
earlier and what is the range name so
you can give the range name some range
name so you can give the range name this
entire range name I want to give it as
probably employee data because I want to
store the employee data within this
table okay so I'm going to make this
as
employee
employee data name this as employee data
okay I named it as employee data now you
need to Define data range what is the
data range see what is the start cell
and your end cell what is the start cell
and end cell
as I told you A1 to b50 correct I'm
going to Define
A1 b
y so done so now I have defined my Excel
range once you define the Excel range
now you need to modify the data or you
need to enter the data that you want to
enter in Excel workbook within the range
right so what I'm going to do now
let's do one thing okay let us do now to
manipulate the range there is an option
operation called
Excel range manipulation so Excel range
manipulation which ma which manipulates
or which modifies the data within the
range
okay so now if you ex see here you have
a range name so what is the range name
that you provided I provided the range
name called employee data copy the same
thing put it
here okay and now expand this data table
let us minimize rest all so that you can
see everything now if you see data table
has a row and
column now first you need to Define
your header need to Define header I want
to name this as let's say first I'm
going to enter the full name column and
then I want to enter the salary of each
employee let's assume salary okay so
that means these two columns I want to
create how can you create that go back
here under row I want to select it as a
header first this is is the header but
what is the cell that you want to
enter I want to in the first
cell on
header in the first cell I want to enter
full name right in the first cell # one
enter it as full name full name and in
your second cell what is that hash2
I want to enter the header as
salary right so done
now I want to fill employees name and
the salary how can we do that so simply
this time again come to the new row your
header row is done now you need to
Define new row how my first row after
header dollar one anytime your first row
after header is dollar
one okay
now
again hash1 which is my first cell of my
first row I'm going to name this as I
mean I want to enter the employee name
as
Ravi
K and for example okay and then what is
the
salary again that is your second s
ash2 let's say salary I would be
defining it as
30,000 or 50,000 let's say
50,000 okay
now your first row is done now I want to
enter another employee so before that I
want to store this salary into your
buffer okay I'm going to do that because
I'm going to perform some calculations
dollar two sorry
hash
two what I'm doing
has to means this cell I'm going to
Define I'm going to tell to store into a
buffer called
amount or do one thing salary one I'm
going to create a buffer here here
change this as buffer and restall also
see here it is taking verify no I don't
want to verify this I want to enter it
so that's why input you need to select
the action mode input for entering the
values
input input but your first row and
header right these are actually select
you're selecting the data table header
you are selecting and then you are
inputting the information now I am
saving or storing the salary of first
employee into a buffer called salary
1 now let us go to our second row dollar
two okay here again my
first
Ash one I want to name this as the
employee
name okay I'm going to put the employee
name and then here
salary okay what is the salary let's say
again
here 40,000 let's assume 40,000 again I
want to store this here you need to
change your action mode don't forget to
change the action mode as input okay so
here now again store hash to the same
cell value into a buffer buffer called
salary
2 and put it into buffer
okay done so now I want to enter last
one I want to enter the last row okay
here dollar three third row in third row
I want to have a total okay total salary
I'm going to
say
hash1 I'm going to mention it as total
amount total amount
and then here I want to calculate the
total amount right in sell two third row
cell two here I want to calculate the
total amount here you need to introduce
the math function what I'm going to do
here if I'm going to explain you what is
this math function okay if you see
math what I'm going to do here salary
one and salary 2
salary two if you see open curly braces
math I already covered all these math
functions in my previous sessions okay I
would recommend you guys to go through
those
sessions open curly braces math and then
open your square bracket and you are
calling your first buffer salary one
plus your second buffer salary 2 and
closing all your parenthesis so if you
click on other cell see now your formula
is correct so here I need to input this
this is my input total and here so what
I'm doing here instead of sorry so
before you verify this right I want to
insert so let me do one thing I want to
remove this formula from here I want to
enter the value first what I'm doing I'm
going to enter the value as 90,000
because your total salary 50,000 +
40,000 is 90,000 right I'm going to
input that and then I'm going to verify
if I inputed correct or not it means
again ash2 I'm going to
calculate salary 1 plus salary 2 should
be 90,000 I'm going to verify if I'm
entering the correct value or not okay
math function so here I'm going to leave
this as
verify let's minimize this
so basically we manipulated everything
but one thing we have to do I don't want
to close the Excel workbook
here I want to close the Excel workbook
and save it after defining Excel range
after entering the data bring this
down right so if you see now my sequence
open Excel book create worksheet Define
your Excel
range and then you are manipulating that
means you are entering the
data in two columns and three rows and
I'm verifying if the total amount is
whatever I entered is correct or Not by
introducing the math
function okay and then I'm closing the
worksheet and where I'm saving the
worksheet okay so now let us run all
these together so before I run let me
close this
workbook and I want to delete the
workbook okay let's delete the
workbook because I have to delete
manually now okay let's delete manually
for now I'll tell you later how to
delete automatically okay right click
and run this now and see what it is
going to do it should
create your Excel workbook
worksheet so now see everything is
passed you also create created your
Excel range also manipulated Excel range
now let us go to our
documents here and date
modified and here open the
workbook see here
now see it entered all the salaries and
it provided total amount and
90,000 right and also if you see it
should verify it should have verified
your total amount correct or not let's
go
here in
uh see here verification is Success your
expected value is 90,000 actually is
90,000 right but if I run this again now
what is happens it's going to fail
because your Excel sheet is already
exist so let's because we
selected create new let's say run this
it says it's going to fail by saying
your Excel already
exist so then what should we do we have
to delete Excel file Whenever there is
three so that means first I need to
delete if the Excel sheet exist then I
need to delete see here says find name
already exist when I'm saving it so that
means I need to introduce another the
test step for deleting the Excel
workbook
delete file
delete file so delete file is one common
operation it's not Excel related but any
file it's going to delete I'm going to
bring this to the
top okay here I'm going to specify the
directory what is the directory of your
Excel
this is the
directory copy
this and what is the file name that you
want to create delete I want to delete
the F name do
xlsx so now if I run this now again if
the Excel sheet exist it deletes if does
not exist it's not going to fail okay
right click and run so now it will
delete the demo. XLS see it deleted now
it creates the new one
and it enters entire the
data done see now it's let's go back to
my documents let's go to documents and
sort it as a modified see I can see
Excel sheet is created and your data has
been entered right hope you all
understand the concepts of excel
operations how can you perform different
Excel operations by using
trien oh you all understand the concepts
of how can you perform different Excel
operations by using tritis stasa please
do subscribe to the channel click on
Bell icon you'll receive notifications
whenever I publish more videos thank you